<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Godlye and holesome preseruatyue against desperatiõ at all times necessarye for the soule but then chiefly to be bled and ministred when the deuill doth assault us moost fiercely, and deth approcheth niest.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20203.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20243271</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20243271</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23916</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23916)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1712:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Godlye and holesome preseruatyue against desperatiõ at all times necessarye for the soule but then chiefly to be bled and ministred when the deuill doth assault us moost fiercely, and deth approcheth niest.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By James Burtel, dwellyng without the northe gate of Paules in the corner house of Pater noster rowe openinge into Chepesyde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A preseruatiue against desperation.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁸.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 20205.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A godlye and holeſome preſeruatyue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all times neceſſarye for the ſoule: but then chiefly to be vſed and miniſtred when the deuill doth aſſault vs mooſt fierſely, and deth approcheth nieſt.</p>
            <q>Be ſobre, and watch, for your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary the deuyll as a roring lyon: walketh about. ſeking who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuoure, whom reſiſt, ſtedfaſt in the fayth. <bibl>1. Pet. 5.</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:2"/>
            <head>The preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His preſeruatiue (gentle reader) is prepared for thy profit: that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it at leaſure maiſt choſe oute ſuche comfortable ſentences as may bothe ſtaye thy owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the tyme of temptacion: &amp; alſo quiet others when the Deuil ſhalbe buſie with them.<note place="margin">2. Cor. ii.</note> For we be not ignoraunte of the thoughtes of ſatan, how he continually fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth him ſelfe, to bende his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce againſt man. And now with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and multitude of ſynne: Now with the terrour of death &amp; damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nacion,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.</note> do labour to beate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buck<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler of faith out of our handes,<note place="margin">i. Teſſ. 5.</note> to ſtrike the helmet of hope from our head:<note place="margin">Eph. 6.</note> And to wreſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſwerd of the ſpirite, which is gods word</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:3"/>
            <p>But here chriſtian reader is thy ſwerd and buckeler deliuered vnto the, here is thy helmette put vpon thy heade, here thou ſhalte finde ſuche armour, and weapon, wherby thou ſhalt both be able to withſtande the forſe of cure com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men enemy the Deuill: and alſo (by thy councell) to reſcue others that they periſhe not. Yea, here y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt find choiſe of moſte comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſentences, wherby mans co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may be ſtaide from damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable deſperation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i. Co. xvi.</note>Watche therfore, ſtande ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte in faithe, playe the man, and be of good comfort,<note place="margin">Iaco. iiii.</note> Reſiſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll, and he will flee frome the. Not for feare of thy own power, ſtrength, or holines: but for feare of Chriſte: in whome by faythe thou art ingraffed. For it is chriſt thorough whome god hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <note place="margin">i. Cor. xv.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:23916:3"/> vs victory againſt ſynne, deathe, hell, &amp; the deuyll.<note place="margin">Acto. iiii.</note> Nether is there any other name vnder heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto man, wherein we may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but the name of Ieſus Chriſte oure lorde. To whome with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and holye ghoſt, be al ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and glorye. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:4"/>
            <head>A preſeruatiue</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orſomuche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſeaſes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy and corporall deathe, dothe ſo trouble mannes mynde, that we commonly trimble and quake at the onely mencion of them: How much ought we to feare the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſoule and death of the ſame, then whiche, there can no greater, nor more fearefull cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytye chaunce vnto man.</p>
            <p>And ſeinge that euery man doth auoyde (ſo muche as in him ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ethe) the payne, myſeryes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and deathe of the bodye: howe much more ought we to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline and eſchewe, the cauſes of theſe euilles, which be ſinnes and offences, and feare the ire of god, which we ſo (by oure enormities) do prouoke. Yf we be neuer ſo ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:23916:4"/> ſick in our body, by and by we ſende for the phiſicion, we ſpare no coſt, we ſeke for medicines and remedye, though they be neuer ſo chargable, &amp; al to patch and clout vp this earthen veſſell of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, whiche do we neuer ſo muche can not laſte longe. And whye vſe we not lyke dylygence in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring, &amp; ſeking remedies againſt the diſeaſes of the ſoule? whiche like as they be more greuous: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo they bring with them (without compariſon) infinitely more daun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger. For what can it profitte a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoughe he haue all the riches in the world, though he liue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yere, and that in ſuch helthe &amp; pleaſure, that he is not once tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched with ſickenes or greife: his ſoule in the meane time being poi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoned with ſinne, being captiue to ſatan, hauyng God diſpleaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:23916:5"/> him, and dampnacion readye for him after this lyfe. For truelye this lyfe muſte once haue an ende nether know we whan, where, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what maner, or how ſoone. Therfore ſaith Chriſte watch for ye nether know the day nor hour when the ſonne of man wyl come.<note place="margin">Mat. xxv.</note> And leſt we this ſhort time of our abode (omittinge thinges mooſt waightye and profitable) ſhulde folow trifulles, &amp; thinges of ſmal price: he hath voucheſaue to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vs an order and as it were a breue, certaine and ſure way: to come vnto true felicite ſaienge. Seke firſt for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of god and righteouſnes therof:<note place="margin">Math. vi.</note> and all thinges ſhalbe added vnto you. Care for lyuynge, care for riches, care for worldly dignitie, world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye fauoure, worldlye eſtimacion and ſuch lyke tranſitory thinges
<pb facs="tcp:23916:5"/> (which in dede doth litle profitte but many times be cauſe bothe of filthie vices and alſo of greuous calamities) doth beſy, doth vexe, doth trouble, doth eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> defatigate vs both daye and night, but in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge for and procuring of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; heuenly thinges: we be moſt negligent, moſt ſlack, moſte dull, moſt forgetfull. And I pray you, what can be a greater blindnes or a more dangerouſe madnes? whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les we be luſtie, whiles we be in helthe, whiles we be in proſperity we ſcaſely thynke vpon any lyfe to come, we remember not once y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhal dye. But when we be in perell, and daunger by ſickenes, and deathe beginnethe to knocke at oure doore. Euen at that ſame houre when we ſhould playe the menne and fyght againſt oure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimy (beinge ſufficiently armed &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:23916:6"/> weponed afore) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begin we firſt to thinke vpon oure armoure to thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our weapon, to think vpon mending of our lyfe. Theſe thinges declare vs to be ſmallye exerciſed ſoudiers to be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſterouſe iudgement, and verye weaklinges in faith. God be mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyfull vnto vs. Amen.</p>
            <p>But yet though a man be neuer ſo old, though the day be neuer ſo far paſt, ſo he amend whiles he is here: eare it be night, his repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce cometh not out of ſeaſon. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles it were to be wiſſhed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man ſhuld differ his repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to his laſt &amp; moſt dangerous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei ſhal haue much a do to ſtande &amp; to defend them ſelues from the aſſaultes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> guiles, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſions of the enemy: which in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of their helth prepared &amp; ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med them ſelues, what then ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:23916:6"/> come of them whiche not fearing god neither minding once repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce hathled a diſſolute filthie and naughtye life? how ſhal thei fighte? howe ſhall they be able to withſtand the force of ſatan?</p>
            <p>¶ Seinge therefore the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people is great, and the miniſters of the goſpel very few, nether able to be euery where to do their office to euery man: I ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing a will to help al men: haue gathered to gether, &amp; writen oute of ſcripture, a certaine brief forme how to admoniſhe, inſtructe, and comfort ſuch as be ſick, that they either reding theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, or hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring them red by others: may con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue certaine hope &amp; perfit conſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, leſt in this moſt dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>flict they faint, geue ouer like cowardes, &amp; ſo be ouercomed &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſh: For this is certain, when ſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is taken w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> extreme ſick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:23916:7"/> &amp; is in daunger of deth, he is aſſawted with diuers many, &amp; gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous tentacions. Firſt it is a gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uous and vehemente tentacion, when he ſeeth the moſt terrible i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of deathe afore his eyes, when he ſeeth, he muſte leue thys light, leue this life, leaue frendes leaue landes, goodes, kinſfolke, father, mother, wife, childern, all thinges, wherin he had here ether pleaſure or comforte. Then ſuche ſynnes as he againſt the will and pleaſure of god hathe committed ſhall ſhewe and preſent them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and ſhal appeare more in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre, and more greuous then euer they ſemed afore, and ſo ſhall won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derouſely vex and torment the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience. Then dethe, iudgemente, hell, dampnacion, as it were in a plumpe, ſhall aſſaut and lay ſege with diuers daungerous engins
<pb facs="tcp:23916:7"/> againſt the olde man of ours.</p>
            <p>In theſe Agonies, except a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be armed with a ſure and conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t faith: it is to be feared, leſte he be weried, tired, and at laſt ouercom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med. For theſe tentacions which chaunce vnto men lyeng in extre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes: appere moſt houge, feareful and daungerouſe, and that for by cauſe our faith is verye ſclender, and waueringe: neither yet able to ſee, perceaue or apprehend, the incomprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſible and ineſtimable riches of the childern of god, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che be remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynnes through chriſte, reſurrection of the fleſh, communion of ſaintes, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge life, and all theſe geuen vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs in Chriſt and for Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In theſe articles of our faithe we muſt dailye exerciſe oure ſelues. Theſe we muſt diligently reuolue and earneſtly expende in our min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des.
<pb facs="tcp:23916:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> For thoughe all the articles of our faith are diligentlye to be remembred and without al waue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ringe beleued: yet in the Agonye and pointe of deathe, theſe foure (that is) the communion of ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, remiſſion of ſinne, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of Chriſte, the reſurrection of the fleſhe, and euerlaſting lyfe: are chiefely to be mynded expended, and inculcated.</p>
            <p>For like as deth is the paine &amp; ſtipend of ſinne:<note place="margin">Roma. 6.</note> euen ſo for ſynne God dothe commenly punyſh vs with diuers diſeaſes and plages, As it is to be ſene i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers places of ſcriptur. Io. 5. Pſ. 88. Deute. 28. 2. Reg. 24.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles afflictions be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny tymes laid vpon vs, that our faith may be tried: For than is it eaſy to be perceauyd howe much we loue GOD, what faithe we
<pb facs="tcp:23916:8"/> haue in him, howe we truſt him, when we be preſſed &amp; greuyd w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aduerſitie. In this caſe therfore we muſt bewaile &amp; acknowlege our ſynnes, for the which we haue iuſtlie incurred goddes diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and deſeruid moſt greuous paine. We muſt turne to God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> true repentaunce in all our hart &amp; mynde, without all faynynge and conterfaitinge, we muſt haue recourſe vnto the Goſpel where we ſhall fynd moſt bountifull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .i. abſolucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſynnes which chriſt hath inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churche Io. 20. Receaue (ſaithe Chriſte) the hollie ghoſte whoſe ſiftes ye forgeue thei are for geaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This ineſtimable treaſure is daily openyd &amp; offred vnto vs.</p>
            <p>When remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne is thus deſired, &amp; optained: vndoutedly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paine of ſinne which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eaſe
<pb facs="tcp:23916:9"/> or afflyccion ſhal ſone ceaſſe and leaue vs, or elles accordinge to the moſt beneficiall will of our heuenly father: ſhall tourne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> profit and ſoule helth of him that is diſeaſed or afflicted, For this maye we be ſure of, that the paine and affliction of the body in this worlde (ſeme it neuer ſo greuous a bourden or heuie yoke to the fleſſhe) is comenly nothinge elles but a fatherlie rod,<note place="margin">Pſal. 88.</note> wherwith god dothe drawe vs his childern fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne, and call vs home to him. Truly our heuinly father dothe loue vs moſte feruentlie, he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithe vs good mynde, and dothe all thinges for our amendemente and profitte,<note place="margin">Heb. xii.</note> for whome God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uithe, him he chaſtiſethe, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectith vs temporally here: that we ſhould not be puniſhed in hell euerlaſtinglie.<note place="margin">1. Cor. xi.</note> Thoughe he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mith
<pb facs="tcp:23916:9"/> angrie: he louithe ſinguler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. Nether is his Ire the Ire of a tyraunt or torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tour deſyringe our perdycion: but of a father ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge our amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſauftie. Firſt therfore we muſt crye God mercy deſire pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; forgeuenes of our ſynnes (but by chriſt, but with a hart trulie penitent) that we may be at one with God, and haue him mercyful vnto vs. This done we maye then deſire GOD to deliuer vs from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Imminent and preſent affliction and diſeaſe. For ſo teacheth eccleſiaſt.<note place="margin">Eccleſi. 3</note> Sonne in thy infirmity neglect not thy ſelf, but pray to the Lord: and he ſhall deliuer the. Alſo in the Pſ.<note place="margin">Pſal. 70.</note> remember not o lord god our old iniquities but let thy mercie ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely preuent vs: for we be verie miſerable, helpe vs God our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. Lord God of power turne
<pb facs="tcp:23916:10"/> vs howe longe wilt thou be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie? ſhewe thy face and we ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſaued. Here we be taught firſte to deſire remiſſion of ſinne, that we may ſo be at one with god: and after that to haue his wrathe, and the tokens of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away. But when ſoeuer we deſire to be deliueryd or to be eaſed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe that preſſeth vs, we muſt alwaye annexe this addicion.<note place="margin">Mar. vi.</note> Thy wil (o heuenly father) be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>Neither knowe we ſo well what is profitable vnto vs. Nether ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſo well prouide for our ſelues as our moſt louing heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father. Which is both of infinite powre: and alſo of incomprehenſible wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which neuer tournethe his eys from vs, which caryth conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually for vs, which knowith the number of our heres, which doth quicken noriſh, fede, kepe, defend
<pb facs="tcp:23916:10"/> prouide for al his creatures much better than thei can wiſh or deſire. But to drawe to the more perticu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler temptacions, &amp; to ſhewe what thinges do moſt fierſly &amp; daunge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rouſly at the time of death aſſault vs. And how we ſhall w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ There be thre thinges, which at the houre of death doth wonderouſly vex, trouble, &amp; feare our myndes (that is to ſaye) ſynne, death, hel or dampnacion.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Synne.</head>
                  <p>WHerein we haue vngodlye miſpent our life, wherby we haue greuouſly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded god and our neighbour: This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to our remembraunce when we lie vpon our death bed, doth driue vs to a wonderous feare,<note place="margin">Roma. ii.</note> penſiue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and anxiety. As ſainct Paule ſaithe, wrathe indignacion trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and anguiſhe againſt euerye ſoule of man that doth euill.</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb facs="tcp:23916:11"/>
                     <head>A medicine againſt ſynne vexinge and troubelinge. our conſcience.</head>
                     <p>LEt vs cal earneſtly to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that the ſonne of God came downe from heuen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came man, toke vp on his backe the ſynnes of the worlde, died for them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, there makinge ſatiſfaction for vs and paing our dettes. This moſt precious blod of chriſt was ſhed alſo for vs, and of this deth we be alſo partakers ſo we rightlie beleue in Chriſte, Nether nede we to doubt but Chriſt died aſwell for vs, as for Peter and Paule:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> For we be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized alſo (as ſainct Paule ſaith) in the deth of Chriſt. This ought to comfort vs, this ought to erect and ſtay our myndes. For ſeinge we be baptized in the dethe of Chriſte. Chriſtes dethe bringeth
<pb facs="tcp:23916:11"/> alſo vnto vs helth and ſaluacion. By Chriſtes deth we be alſo dead to ſynne: by Chriſtes deathe we haue alſo certaine and ſure remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſynnes, by Chriſtes dethe we be raiſed alſo to a newe and euerlaſtinge life. For bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time is a couenand betwixt God and vs. And a ſigne of his grace and fauour towarde vs wherin we be reconciled and made at one with god againe, ſo that we may nowe haue a ioyfull and quiet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for ſomoche as our ſynnes be forgeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, through the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Ieſus chriſt. Yea chriſt alſo in the inſtitucion of the moſt bleſſed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his laſt ſupper ſpeaketh alſo to vs ſaing, that his blood is ſhed for the remiſſion of ſynne. Nowe although we haue not liued alwaie innocentlie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther led ſuche a lyfe as we ought
<pb facs="tcp:23916:12"/> to haue done: Yet we maye not diſpayre, but w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out delaye reſort vnto god, by true repentaunce, cal faithfullye vpon his name, and we ſhalbe ſaued.<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> Ye let euery one of vs with a meke harte burſt out in to theſe, or like wordes and ſay O moſte mercifull God, father of al mercy, father of oure LORD Ieſu Chriſte, be mercyfull vnto me a wretched ſynner, make ſpede to deliuer me, for the moſt bitter (but mooſt precious) death, and paſſion of Ieſu Chriſte thy onlie begotten ſonne, oure redemer, and only ſauioure: Amen. Enter not (o lord) in to iudgement with thy feruaunte, handle me not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to my deſeruinge, nether do vnto me after my iniquities: but accordinge to thy infinite and botomles goodnes &amp; mercy take me vnto the. I a miſerable and
<pb facs="tcp:23916:12"/> wretched creature am i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy hand, I am in thy debt &amp; daunger, thou mayſt do with me what it pleaſe the. O mooſte mercifull father forſake me not, nether caſt me of. I am thine all that I am. There can no man comfort, no man help no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deliuer me, but thou alone. Thou art the true comfort, the moſt preſent helpe, the ſureſt bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke in all neceſſitie. Thou god art my refuge, my ſtrength, my helpe in al trouble. Thou art my Lord in thy handes reſteth al my chaunce and affaires. Shewe thy louing and mercyfull face vpon thy ſeruaunt, ſaue me in thy mercy O lord: but in any ways in our extreme ſicknes and affliction, let vs beware we loke not to earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neither to longe vpon our ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But rather let vs haue the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Chriſtes moſte helthfull
<pb facs="tcp:23916:13"/> and precious deth before our eys. Let vs fix that in our mynd and be fully perſuaded that Chriſt is now bourdened with our ſynnes, that he hathe nowe taken theim vpon his owne ſhoulders and ſo hathe ſatiſfied for theim and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed them away, that he wil neuer charge vs with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but frelie for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geaue vs theim as we profeſſe in our Crede. whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſay <hi>Credimus remiſſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> we beleue the remyſſion of ſynnes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Here it ſhalbe mete that in our ſicknes we call to remebraunce ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of holie ſcripture as teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth of remiſſion of ſynne purchaſed by Chriſte of the which ſome be here ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Io. i.</note>BEhold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lambe of god which takith away the ſynne of the world.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23916:13"/>
                     <p>We are bought with no golde,<note place="margin">i. Pet. i.</note> nor ſiluer, nether any corruptible price, but with the precious blood of the vnſpotted and vndefyled lambe Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
                     <p>So god hath loued the world that he gaue his onlie begotten ſonne to thende that we ſo bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge in him ſhould not periſhe but haue lyfe euerlaſtinge.<note place="margin">Io. iii.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>I come not to call the righteous but the ſynners to repentaunce.<note place="margin">Mar. ix.</note> Come vnto me al ye that laboure and are laden and I ſhall refreiſh you. Lo he calleth al, he refuſeth,<note place="margin">Math. xi.</note> he excludeth none, we muſt includ alſo our ſelues within this worde (All) we muſt reſorte to him, and he will receaue and refreſh vs.</p>
                     <p>God ſetteth forth his loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs. For Chriſt died for vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> when we were yet ſinners, muche more now therfore we being iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied
<pb facs="tcp:23916:14"/> by his blood ſhalbe ſauffe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wrath by him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. cor. i.</note>Chriſt Ieſus is becommed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs wiſdome, rightouſnes, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; redempcion. Here let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> though we haue be neuer ſo great ſinners, let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and knowledge our ſinne, let vs call for mercy and pardon, let vs vnfainedly beleue Chriſt to be our only helth Iuſtice, and rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: and ſtraight waye he is ſo, he will by and by couer and put away our ſynnes in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhal nede fere no peril nor dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">ii. co. v.</note>Him that knew no ſinne, hath god made ſinne .i. a paymente of ſinne for vs, that we ſhulde beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the righteouſnes of god by him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Gala. i.</note>Chriſt gaue him ſelfe for oure ſinnes that he might deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wicked world accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the wil, of god our father.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23916:14"/>
                     <p>In Chriſt we haue redempcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorough his bloude,<note place="margin">Epheſi. i.</note> euen the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes according to the riches of his grace.</p>
                     <p>Chriſt Ieſus is come into this worlde to ſaue ſynners.<note place="margin">i. Ti. i.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſt Ieſus hath geuin him ſelf a redemption for al men.<note place="margin">i. Ti. ii</note> This let vs conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly beleue &amp; vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted we be of the number of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe ſaued. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is come a redemption for all, theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath ſuffered pertaineth no leſſe to the &amp; me, &amp; euery one of vs (ſo we beleue) than to Peter or Paule.<note place="margin">i. Pe. ii.</note> Chriſt hath borne our ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in his body vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe.</p>
                     <p>Chriſt died once for our ſinnes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteous for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnrighteous.<note place="margin">i. petr. iii</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The bloud of Ieſus chriſt cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs from al ſinne.<note place="margin">i. Io. i.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yf any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth ſinne we haue a aduocate w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the father eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus<note place="margin">i. Ioan. ii</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23916:15"/> Chriſt the righteouſe and he is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> attonemente for our ſynnes: Not for ours onely: but for the ſinnes of the whole worlde.</p>
                     <p>By theſe places and ſuche like we maye ſe howe god the father (which wil not the death of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but that we ſhulde turne and liue) for that moſt feruent &amp; bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning loue that he beareth toward vs, hath eaſed vs of the burden of our ſin, &amp; hath laide it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> back of his moſt dere beloued ſonne. which his ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne hath ſo take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, borne and ſuffered for them: that they can neuer condemne vs. For god taketh and reputeth the death of his ſonne for a full ſatiſfaction &amp; paiment for al our ſinnes, ſo that we truly beleue in him: For ſeing that our ſinnes thus laide vpon Chriſte could not ouercome him, detain him in deth, nor da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne him
<pb facs="tcp:23916:15"/> (for why he roſe againe) vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly a full ſatiſfaccion is alredy made for them, the iuſtice of god is fully anſwered, and they be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly hid and forgeuen. Let vs be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue this and we ſhall not periſhe euerlaſtignly. For Chriſt is now become ours, with al that he hath with his death, with his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with his aſſencion into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, with his life,<note place="margin">Qui proprio filio ſuo non pepercit.</note> his merits his glorie. As ſaint Paule witneſſe. Rom. viii. wherfore Satan hath nowe no title to vs, he can not me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dle with vs, he hath no power to hurt vs. Forſomuch as we be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by chriſt, purged from our ſinnes, and made the children of god by Chriſt who hath reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vs &amp; wrought our peace, we muſt therfore be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte. For ſeinge we be in the handes of god, that is omnipotent, who is
<pb facs="tcp:23916:16"/> now our beſt moſt louing, &amp; truſty father we be in a ſure porte, we be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our daunger, there ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no incom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modity nor aduerſitie hurt vs, for we be inuironed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cuſtody of god, &amp; the gard of angels, oute of the handes of this heuenly father can no creature by force pluck vs When we be at an ende by death of this croſſe and corporal afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then haue we ended our iour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney, then haue we finiſhed oure warre: Chriſte hathe borne the ſame croſſe, Chriſte hathe paſſed the ſame waye, he hathe ſuffered like deathe, he is oure heade we muſte be like to him, we muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if we intend to raigne with him, we muſt leue this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall lyfe, ere that we can inioye lyfe euerlaſtinge. Lette not oure ſynnes trouble vs, lette them not tormente oure conſcience, as
<pb facs="tcp:23916:16"/> though they coulde not be forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. They are alredy forgeuen, yf we repent and beleue: Chriſt is al ours as muche as he is. He by his innocency hath couered and taken awaye oure ſynnes. As Chriſte can not be dampned, euen ſo we can not be dampned, yf with a ryghte faithe, we cleaue vnto hym. As ſynne, deathe, and hell, hadde no power againſt Chryſte ſo haue they no power againſt vs ſo we be in Chriſte, and Chryſte in vs. Yf the matter hadde be left and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to vs to haue borne our owne ſynnes, and to haue ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied for them, they wolde haue be to heuie for vs, we had not be able to ſtande vnder theym they wolde haue preſſed and ſunke vs downe to hell. But chriſte bothe god and man hath (of his owne
<pb facs="tcp:23916:17"/> free will) offered him ſelfe for vs. he hath taken our turne, he hathe plaide our part, and paide for vs all that we ought. As it is in the Pſalme ſpoken in the perſon of chriſte, I paid that I ought not. We had treſpaſed, we were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> det<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo farre behind hand, that all that was in vs, was not able to paie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſt ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me we ought. Chriſte became our ſuertie, paid for vs, ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quited vs, and ſet vs at libertie. yea, made vs coheires with him of euerlaſtinge glorye.</p>
                     <p>Yf it were poſſible for one man to commit the ſinnes of the whole worlde, ſo he truely repente and cleaue by true faith to Chriſte, he can not be dampned, his ſynnes be ſufficiently and abundantly by Chriſte ſatiſfied for. For Chriſte (as towchinge his godhed one in ſubſtance with the heuinlie father
<pb facs="tcp:23916:17"/> As towchinge his manhede our very fleſhe and blood) hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed, and trulie bought grace and pardon for vs. For Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came man for vs, was borne for vs, died vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe for vs, roſe from dethe for vs, aſcended into heuin for vs, and hath accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and performed all thinges mete for our ſaluacion, for vs. Yf therfore we beleue in chriſt we are become partakers of gods fauor we are eaſed of the packe &amp; bourde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſynne, we are made the heires of god and coheires with Chriſte for euer, and that by Chriſt and for Chriſt. For without Chriſt there is no conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no helth no hope, no helpe. In Chriſte alone is all comforte, all helth, all hope, all ſuccour, all refuge, all grace and mercy more habundant more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, more excellent than any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23916:18"/> is able either to comprehend or to wiſhe. God graunte vs therfore a true and a conſtant faith. In this forme or in like ſort we muſt com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort our ſelues in our ſickenes or calamitie, and our brother beinge viſited. But in any wais and with al dilygence it is to be foreſeene, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we withdrawe oure mynde from the fearefull and terrible contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placion of ſynne, death, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion. And that we fixe theſe of our mynd and whole thoughte v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Chriſt only, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we cleue vnto him, that we cal vpon him, that we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit our ſelf wholy to him. For in Chriſte we ſhal eſpie nothing but innocencie, iuſtice, life, ſaluacion, which al be deriued from Chriſte into vs, ſo that we will acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, &amp; receaue him for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of our ſaluacion and only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demer. yf we haue chriſt crucified
<pb facs="tcp:23916:18"/> afore our eys: yf we imprinte him in our hart, yf we flee to him with our faith: if we wholy cleue to him. Then ſhal hel gates nothing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt vs, then ſhall we be able to withſtand al the forcible aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaultes of Satan, though they be neuer ſo ſore, neuer ſo fierce, neuer ſo terrible.</p>
                     <p>Let vs cal to remembraunce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what lenitie, what ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tilnes, what humanitie, what clemency Chriſte (as it is in the euangelical hiſtory) hath called vnto him and receued al ſuche ſinners as hath repented them, and deſired his helpe. We ſhall finde Mary Magdalen, the ſynner that honge vpon the right hand of chriſt crucified, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licane, zache, with other mo whom Chriſte moſt louingly receiuinge pronounced clere fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, (though they had ſynned greatlye) and the childern of ſaluacion, Chriſte is
<pb facs="tcp:23916:19"/> very grace, mercy, helpe, comfort, life, ioye, and ſaluacion to al thoſe which loke for theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges at his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des: and put their truſt in him. And all theſe thinges hathe God (who is truethe it ſelf &amp; can not lie nor will not deceyue) promyſed vnto vs for chriſtes ſake.</p>
                     <p>Fynallie whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deth approcheth we muſt do as Chriſte dyd vpon the croſſe, we muſt praie for our enemyes and forgeaue them with our harte. Yf we haue offended any man we muſt be hartelie ſorye for it, we muſt deſire forgeuenes. yf we haue iniured any man, we muſt make him amendes, or take ſuche order that amendes maie be made vnto him. yf it paſſithe our power to make reſtitucion and amendes: it ſhalbe ynoughe that we deſire forgeauenes. And with our hartes forgeaue others which
<pb facs="tcp:23916:19"/> hath hurt vs either in name, bodie ſubſtance or eſtimacion. For yf we trulie forgiue: god hathe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed we ſhalbe forgiuen as it is in the ſyxt of Mathew.</p>
                     <p>It is verie neceſſarie alſo and profitable for the confirmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſtrenghteninge of our faithe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the moſte bleſſed ſacrament of the bodie and blood of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our chriſt which we ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to receaue in remembraunce of his benefites, that hereby, we maie be trulie certified in our conſcience his body to be geuen for vs, and his blood to be ſhed for remiſſion of our ſynnes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Dethe</head>
                  <p>OF our fleſſhe &amp; fraill nature is ſo feared &amp; abhorred y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he approcheth, mans hart is filled and laden with ſuche ſorowes, panges, and anxieties as tonge is
<pb facs="tcp:23916:20"/> not able to expreſſe.</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>A medicine againſt the feare of death.</head>
                     <p>WE muſte call to our remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce dethe to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed and aboliſhed by Chriſte. So that nowe the ſoules of ſo many as truſt in Chriſt, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not die nor periſhe: but departinge frome the body goeth ſtraight to chriſte. For thus was it ſaide to the thefe at his houre of death. This daie ſhalt thou be with me in paradiſe. The bodye thoughe it reſte and pauſe for a while yet we be in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hope that at the laſte daye it ſhalbe raiſed againe to immortall and euerlaſting lyfe. And therfore ſcripture calleth the deathe of the body but a ſlepe, for that this ſame fraile, weke, vyle, mortal and cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruptible bodye, which we carie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, which lieth ſicke &amp; ſore diſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, which ſhortly ſhalbe put into
<pb facs="tcp:23916:20"/> the earth, burnt to aſſhes, deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beſtes or foules, drowned in water, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſelf body (I ſay) ſhal be raiſed again incorruptible, glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious, bewtifull, ſtronge,<note place="margin">i. cor. xv.</note> pure im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mortall to poſſeſſe a newe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge lyfe: where there ſhal neither be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, thirſt, heat, cold, ſynne, deth nor any kynde of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, but iuſtice, innocencye, lyfe, ioye, bleſſe, world withoute ende. For as the body of Chriſte laid in the graue roſe againe the thirde day neuer more to die. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodies of al that beleue in chriſt at the later day be reſuſcitate to a lyfe, after whiche ſhall folowe no death. God who is of infinite po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and infallible truth hath pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſed theſe thynges, they muſte therfore nedes be ſo. And here it ſhalbe profitable to call to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce ſuche places of ſcripture
<pb facs="tcp:23916:21"/> as treatith of the reſurrection of the fleſh, which be the wordes not of man but of god. who is able &amp; will certainly fulfill what ſoeuer he hathe ſpoken. No man can chaunge his wil, no man can alter his purpoſe. No creature can fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, let, or tarie his ſentence. He is omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, he is true, he is faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full, his goodnes and mercie is inexplicable. Let no man therfore doubt of the treuthe of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des let no man doubt of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formaunce of his promiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Herafter folowithe certayne places of ſcripture witneſſinge the reſurrection of the dead according to this article of our faith wherin we ſaie we beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this fleſh ſhall riſe againe.<note place="margin">Iohn. vi.</note>
                     </head>
                     <p>THis is the will of my Father which ſente me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer ſeith the ſonne &amp; beleuithe in him ſhall haue life euerlaſtinge and I
<pb facs="tcp:23916:21"/> will raiſt him vp againe in the laſt daye.</p>
                     <p>The houre comithe wherin all they that be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grauys ſhal here the voice of the ſonne of God and ſhall go forthe thei that haue done good vnto the reſurrection of life.<note place="margin">Iohan. v</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>For if ſo be that the ſpirit of him which rayſed vp Ieſus from the dead dwell in you:<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> euin he that raiſed vp Ieſus Chriſte from the dead ſhall alſo quicken your mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall bodyes becauſe of his ſprite that dwelleth in you.</p>
                     <p>God hathe bothe raiſed vp oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt and ſhal alſo raiſe vs vp by his power.<note place="margin">i. Cor. vi.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Chriſte ſaithe Lazarus was but a ſlepe where in verie dede he was dead and buried.<note place="margin">Iohan. xi</note> But Chriſt is the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and life (as it is in the ſame place) ſo that he that beleuethe on him thoughe he were
<pb facs="tcp:23916:22"/> dead he ſhall lyue, In verefienge whereof he raiſed ſtraighte waye Lazarus being foure dayes dead and ſtynkynge. And becauſe we be naturallye in the agonye of deathe verye fearefull, weake and faintherted: to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might be the eaſelier perſwaded in the ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticle of reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Scripture ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth mencion of manye whiche in the time of the prophetes, Chriſte, and thappoſtles were called from deathe to lyfe,</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Luc. 7.</note>Chriſt rayſed the widowes ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Luc. 8.</note>He raiſed the ruler of the ſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goge his daughter.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Ioa. xi.</note>He raiſed Lazarus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Act. ix.</note>Peter reſtored to life Tabitha.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Act. xx.</note>Paule raiſed again Eutichus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">iiii. Re. 4.</note>Elizeus the prophet called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to lyfe his hoſtes ſonne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">iii. re. xvii</note>Helias raiſed the babe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Sareptanie.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23916:22"/>
                     <p>God toke alſo vnto him out of this frail and tranſitory lyfe,<note place="margin">Gen. 5. 4. Reg. ii.</note> theſe two excellent and holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Enoch and Helias quicke bothe bodye &amp; ſoule, to giue vs (as it were) a taſt and repreſentacion of the true lyfe to come, leſt after the opinion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ethnickes and epicures we ſhulde thinke there were no worlde, nor beinge after this wretched &amp; miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable life. Let vs not forget what chriſt Ieſꝰ lord of life, &amp; deth, ſaith in the .viii. of Luke, wepe not, the maid is not dead but a ſlepe. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſteries of god, nether perceiuing his power doth laugh this ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to ſcorne, but chriſt prouethe his ſaing true, he raiſeth by &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead maid to life.</p>
                     <p>The .xv. chapter of the firſt epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle to the Corin. is repleniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſte godly pleaſaunt and pithie conſolacions. Trulye it is more
<pb facs="tcp:23916:23"/> precious than anye golde. For in that Chapit. ſaincte Paule dothe ſo annexe and couple our reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to the reſurcection of chriſt as though thei coulde in no wiſe be ſeperate or diuided after this forme. Chriſt is riſen from death (which thing is certain) ergowe al ſo ſhal vndoutedly riſe. For chriſt is our head and we his membres: This head is neither without ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will forſake his membres. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it foloweth that where chriſt is, there ſhall we be. For why, we are the membres of his bodie and euin of his fleſſhe and bone,<note place="margin">Epheſi. 5.</note> what tonge, what penne, what witte is able to ſet forthe (as it is worthy) this ineffable, &amp; ineſtimable glory of the mercy and grace of god, that God hathe vouchſafe ſo lowe to humble him ſelf as to become mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall man that this feble and fraile
<pb facs="tcp:23916:23"/> nature of man vnited and knit to the diuine nature by the power &amp; efficacie of the godhead, might be inhaunced &amp; promoted to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. For trulie the nature of all faithfull men which ether were before chriſt, hathe be ſens, ar now or ſhalbe to the worldes ende: vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doubtedlie in chriſt verie god and man hathe optained imortality. The conſolacion therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> riſeth of chriſtes reſurrection is of great efficacitie, As when ſainct Paule ſaithe to the Corinthians: Chriſt,<note place="margin">i. Cor. xv,</note> is riſen againe from deade, and is the firſt fruictes of theim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſlepe for by one man truli came death &amp; by one man cometh the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. And as al die i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Adame: euin ſo ſhall all be made aliue in chriſt, but euerie one in his order. The firſt is chriſt. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they which are chriſtes which hathe beleued
<pb facs="tcp:23916:24"/> in his commi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. And ſaincte Paul dothe adde a ſimilitude taken of naturall thinges wher by he doth ſet forthe and declare the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of bodies. The ſimilitude is taken of ſede which caſt into the earthe by the huſbandman dieth as it were and rotteth. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the leſſe it is not vtterlie loſt but at lenght ſpringeth &amp; cometh forthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, goodlie, beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; pleaſaunte. So our bodyes ſhall riſe againe not feble, vyle, corruptible, mortall: but ſtronge glorious incorruptible, immortal neuer to die again but euer to liue</p>
                     <p>The way in to true and euerla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtinge lyfe to our longe home (as they call it) and contrey is by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death. Fleſhe and blood be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge corruptible and mortal can not inherit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god wher nothing is but life. Therfore this
<pb facs="tcp:23916:24"/> corruptible body muſt put on i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; thys mortal muſt put on immortality.<note place="margin">Ore. xiiii. Eſa. xxv.</note> Than ſhal the ſaing that is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be fulfilled. Death is ſwalowed vp in victory. They that beleue in Chriſt hath nowe ouercomed ſynne, deathe, and hel. Therfore not fearinge deathe but ſtronge, bold, and wel harted in Chriſte: they may ſaye deathe where is thy ſting? death where is thy victorie? The ſtinge of deathe is ſynne, and the power of ſynne is the lawe. But thankes be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to god which hathe geauen vs the victorie through our lorde Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
                     <p>Let vs heare alſo more ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces full of godly and mightie conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion.</p>
                     <p>He that hathe raiſed vp Ieſus ſhall raiſe vs vp alſo with Ieſus.<note place="margin">ii. Cor. iiii</note>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23916:25"/>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Phili. iii.</note>Our conuerſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is in heuin fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence we do loke for the ſauiour our lorde Ieſus chriſt which ſhal chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge our vile body y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be like faſhioned vnto his glorious bodie according to the workinge of his power, by the which alſo he is able to ſubdue all thinges vnto him ſelf.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Col. iii.</note>Ye are dead and your life is hid with chriſt in god, but when chriſt your life ſhall appere then ſhal ye alſo appere in glorie with him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Teſſo. 4.</note>We woulde not (brethern) that ye ſhuld be ignorant concerninge them that ſleepe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye ſorowe not alſo as other do whiche haue no hope. For yf we beleue that Ieſus chriſt died and roſe againe: euin the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo which are a ſlepe, through Ieſus ſhal God bringe with him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">ii. Tim. ii</note>Sainct Paule alſo doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte Timothe with the article of
<pb facs="tcp:23916:25"/> reſurrection ſaing. Remembre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the lord Ieſus Chriſt beinge the ſeed of Dauid roſe again from the dead accordinge to my goſpell. And if we be dead with him we ſhall alſo liue with him. Yf we ſuffer pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly we ſhal alſo raign with him.</p>
                     <p>It is writen alſo to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebreus that Chriſte taſted deathe for all men,<note place="margin">Hebre. ii.</note> and that he was partaker of fleſche and bloode .i. became ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he might deſtroy him which had the rule of death (that is) the deuil, and that he might deliuer theim which were in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage all their life tyme, by the reaſon of the feare of death.</p>
                     <p>God hathe deliueryd vs,<note place="margin">ii. Tim. i.</note> and called vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an holie calling, not accordinge to our workes but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his purpoſe &amp; grace whiche is geauen vs in Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:23916:26"/> Ieſu before the tyme of the world but is nowe made manifeſt by the apperinge of oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt which trulie hath deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death and hathe brought life and immortalitie to lighte by the goſpell.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Io. iii.</note>We knowe that we are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated frome life to death becauſe we loue the brethern.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">i. Io. 4.</note>In this hathe the loue of god apperid in vs, becauſe God ſent his onlie begotten ſonne into the world y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might liue through him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Iob. xix.</note>I knowe that my redemer dothe liue, and in the laſt daie I ſhall riſe againe, and againe be wrapped in my owne ſkine. And in my owne fleſſhe ſhall ſee God, whome I my ſelf ſhall ſee &amp; theſe my eyes ſhall beholde and none other:</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23916:26"/>
                     <p>Theſe places of hollie ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſuche like, if we diligent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre &amp; faithfullie imbrace: we ſhall perceaue great conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and conforte,<note place="margin">Phi. iii.</note> And euin with ſaincte Paule reioyſe, that we knowe chriſte and the power of his reſurrection, wherby deth is ouercomed. Nether is there nowe (to theſe that beleue in Chriſt) any thinge in deathe terrible or to be feared, ſauinge onlye the Image and outwarde forme, hurt it can not. Like as a dede ſerpent kea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pith ſtil his old fearful ſhape and forme: but to ſtinge or do harme he hathe no power at al. And like as by the braſin ſerpente whiche Moſes by goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente ſette vp in deſerte when it was loked vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of goddes woord men were deliuerid frome daunger of the
<pb facs="tcp:23916:27"/> liuelie and venyme ſerpentes ſo our deathe is made harmles and we deliuered frome the fear and daunger of it, ſo oft as with the eys of our faithe we do beholde the helthefull and medicinable dethe of Chriſte. In concluſion deathe is nowe become but a I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and ſhadowe of deathe, yea the entraunce and gate to life. For Chriſt who is trueth it ſelf ſaithe. Yf any man kepe my worde,<note place="margin">Io. viii</note> he ſhall neuer ſee deathe, For a man truſtinge to the mercy of God, through faithe, which he concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uith by heringe of Chriſtes goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: is ſo vnite and knitt to chriſt his lorde and maiſter, that he can not be plucked nor ſeperate from him.</p>
                     <p>The body in dede for a tyme is ſeperate from the ſoule but in certaine hope of riſinge againe to
<pb facs="tcp:23916:27"/> euerlaſtinge life. And ſo he that beleuithe in Chriſte dothe not ſee nor fele the euerlaſtinge dethe of body and ſoule, which is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtinge dampnacion, For the deathe of good men is nothinge els but a departure from this tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory and mortal life: to immortality to chriſt, to his angelles and ſainctes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hell and dampnacion</head>
                  <p>DOth offer it ſelf at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hour of death, ſo that manye tymes man doth greatly feare leſt he be abiect fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fauour of god and appoynted to euerlaſtyng payne:
<pb facs="tcp:23916:28"/> The deuyll (which ſeketh by all meanes howe to deuoure vs) ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe vp in oure myndes manye daungerous and troubellous thoughtes, concerninge our elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and predeſtinacion.</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>A medicine againſt the feare of hel and dampnacion.</head>
                     <p>WHen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil goeth about to cauſe vs to dyſpaire or to doubt of our election: whether we be of the numbre of theim that are appointed to euerlaſtinge life or no, In any wais let vs not be to boulde in copinge with him, let vs not enter diſputacion a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt him (for he is to ſubtile and expert for vs) but ſay ſhortly vnto him Away Satan with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, it is writen, thou ſhalt not tempt the lord thy God, For ſeing that god as a moſt louinge father
<pb facs="tcp:23916:28"/> hathe not only geauen vs life. fedde and preſeruid vs, to this houre: but alſo hathe indued and euen loden vs from tyme to time with his ſinguler benefites. what madnes were it contrary to our former experience, nowe to dout of his mercy? He hathe receauyd vs in to his flocke by baptime.</p>
                     <p>He hathe ſente vs the goſpell of his grace, wherein he hathe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to become oure father. we haue be fedde with the fleſſhe and bloode of his ſonne oure ſauioure CHRISTE in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce that oure debtes be paide and we acquited, whye ſhoulde we nowe then doubte of the good will of GOD towarde vs? lette vs not therefore admitte the dout<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and daungerous Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacions of oure predeſtinacion
<pb facs="tcp:23916:29"/> which the deuill like a craftie and malicyous marchaunt doth labor to iuſtill. But let vs thinke vpon ſuche ſentences as God would haue our myndes occupied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, whiche Chryſt him ſelfe hath preſcribed, as Iohn .iii. where he ſayethe. GOD hathe ſo loued the worlde, that he hathe geuyn his onelye begotten ſonne, that whoſoeuer beleuythe in him ſhall not periſhe, but haue life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge. Loo here we ſee that he whiche beleuithe in Chriſt, which faythfullye acknowlegeth chriſt, to be his ſanctifycacyon, iuſtyce, redemption and ſatiſfaccion: can not be dampned, but is aſſured of euerlaſtynge lyfe. So manye as conceaue faithe by hearynge of Goddes worde: and ſo truſt ſted faſtelye vpon the mercy of chriſt: Vndoubtedlye they be of the num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:23916:29"/> of thoſe which be choſen to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtyng blyſſe, knowen before in CHRIST predeſtinate, and wrytten long ſith, in the boke of lyfe. Theſe thynges be mooſte certaine, and mooſt true, God can neither deceaue nor be deceaued.<note place="margin">Rom. viii</note> Such is his good wyll, ſo hathe he purpoſed and decreed afore the worlde beganne, what thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſoeuer therefore oure enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye the deuyll (ſpytynge our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, and ſekynge our deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon) ſhall put in our mynde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to this doctryne. Let them not moue vs, lette them not make vs afrayde, but lette vs truſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in chryſte: and ſo ſhall he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come oures, and we become his, who beyng our good LORD, we can not peryſſhe nor be damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.<note place="margin">Io. x.</note> For he wyl loſe none of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:23916:30"/> that his father hathe geuen him. we muſte fyxe oure eyes vppon Chryſte, we muſte flee to hym, we muſte cleaue to hym. He is oure onelye and true ſauyoure, who muſte be apprehended and imbraced by faythe, yf we loke to be ſaued. For they that beleue ryghtelye in Chriſt, they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate to euerlaſtynge lyfe. Here we muſte diligentlye reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre and earneſtelye expende the godly exhortacion of ſaynt Paul which he writeth in the .xii. to the Hebrewes, whoſe words be theſe, Lette vs runne by pacyence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the battell that is ſette afore vs,<note place="margin">He. xii.</note> lokynge vnto Ieſus, the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore and finiſher of faithe, whiche when the ioye was ſet afore hym, ſuffered the croſſe, and dyſpyſed the ſhame, and ſitteth at the right hand of the ſeate of GOD:</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23916:30"/>
                     <p>Furthermore all the greuous tentacions and afflictions that CHRISTE ſuffered, he ſufferyd them for oure ſakes. As ſaincte Paule ſaithe alſo in the iiii. to the hebrues.<note place="margin">He. iiii.</note> We haue not a highe prieſt that is not able to haue compaſſion on our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: but ſuche one as was prouyd in all pointes without ſynne, let vs therfore with bouldnes go vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the ſeate of his grace, that we may obtaine mercy and fynde grace to help in tyme of nede: Let vs in any ways conſider, and deplie imprinte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our harts, chriſt to be geuin vnto vs, not only to thend y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we might be redemid, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled &amp; made partakers of euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſtinge ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him we might haue an example, bothe howe to liue, and alſo how to end oure life. Nether can any man
<pb facs="tcp:23916:31"/> liue, ſuffer or dye well: vnles he loke vpon and folowe the life, ſufferinge and dethe of Chriſt. yf therfore we deſire to end this life well and godlie: let vs conſider and remembre howe Chriſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued him ſelf in that bitter and ſmart agonie, when hanginge vpon the croſſe, he was aſſaulted with diuers fyerſſe and moſt gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous temtacions, and pray that we may haue grace to folowe his example.</p>
                     <p>Firſt he was temptyd with ſyn, whan beinge hanged betwixt two theues as a notable &amp; hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſynner: it was ſaid vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf thowe beiſt the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">mat. xxvii</note> come downe from the croſſe. By this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelious voice what do they ſignifie elles, but that they iudged him a noughtie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
<pb facs="tcp:23916:31"/> perſon, ſuch one as by craft ſubtiltye, falſheade, ſoſſery, and other vnlawfull meanes had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued the people, hadde blinded the worlde, and to be nothinge leſſe then the ſonne of GOD. Euen in lyke maner at the houre of deathe doth the deuyll tempte man, what ſoeuer man hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſte god, al the ſinnes that euer he dyd, he ſheweth vnto hym, he doth exaggerate them to the vttermoſte, to thende that the multitude and hainouſnes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſidered and perceauid, manne ſhulde doubte of the mercye and fauoure of god, and ſo fall into deſperacion. Here we had nede to ſtande ſure. And euery one of vs had nede to aunſwer our enemye, thus temptinge vs after this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner I knowlege my ſelfe to haue ſynnes aboue all numbre, and
<pb facs="tcp:23916:32"/> meaſure but Chriſte, who neuer ſynned, in whoſe mouth was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d no guile. who is that verye inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent lambe, hathe ſuffered deathe for my ſynnes, he hathe waſſhed them awaye, he hathe ſatyſfied aboundantlye for them,<note place="margin">Eſa. liii.</note> howe ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny and howe greate ſo euer they were. Chriſtes deathe partaineth alſo to me, he was wounded alſo for my iniquities, he was bruſed for my vngraciouſenes, by his ſtrypes I am alſo healed. All my ſynnes hath CHRISTE taken to hym ſelfe, ſo that nowe I haue none (thankes be to CHRISTE) who hathe ſatyſfyed for theym in hys owne bodye.</p>
                     <p>CHRISTE was tempted alſo with death, when it was ſayde vnto hym: he hathe ſaued other,<note place="margin">Mat. xx7</note> but he canne not ſaue hym
<pb facs="tcp:23916:32"/> ſelfe. (As though it ſhoulde be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaide) he is nowe at appointe, he muſte dye, there is no remedye, he can not eſcape. Thus dothe oure olde and irreconciliable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my labour to feare vs with death but let vs holde out the buckeler of faythe in Chriſt againſte hym. Lette vs remember that Chriſte our Lorde, kynge of glorye, and prynce of lyfe, coulde not be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commed nor holden of death, but thoughe he once taſted of death: he nowe lyueth and raigneth for euer. Thys LORDE of ours wyll not leaue vs, nor ſuffer deathe to execute anye tyrannye agaynſte vs, that after he hathe ſuffered vs to be tempted a while he wyll alſo that we dye corporal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly: al that is wholy for our welth. Neyther coulde we other wayes
<pb facs="tcp:23916:33"/> come to euerlaſting life but by temporall deathe. We muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore leaue this preſent life, ere we can inherite the eternal life. Alſo this corporall deathe bringethe this comoditie that by taſtinge the bitternes and ſowernes of it: we haue experience and knowe the excedinge loue that Chriſte bare toward vs, and the ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable benefitt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he did for vs, in clenſinge our ſynnes, in aboliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhynge of death, in breaking vp of hel gates, and al by his death. Other ways we could neuer haue knowen the power of chriſt in aboliſhinge of death, we could neuer haue iuſtly eſtemed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of this benefit, we could neuer haue ſene how iuſt cauſe we haue to giue thankes, to chriſt our lord and redemer. Chriſte liuinge truly, we ſhall alſo liue.
<pb facs="tcp:23916:33"/> and this corporall deth to vs ſhal be nothinge elles but a ſwete and holſome ſlepe, an intraunce and gate in to the true &amp; bleſſed lyfe. For after this tranſitory lyfe then beginne we firſt truly to lyue.</p>
                     <p>THirdly Chriſt was tempted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hel, or euerlaſtynge dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was ſaid vnto him, he hath truſted in GOD let him now delyuer him yf he wyll. As thoughe they ſhould ſay. Nowe it appearethe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hathe hoped in god in vain. For god wyl none of hym, he hathe forſaken hym, he likethe hym not, he dothe abhorre hym, he will caſte hym downe to hell &amp; perpetualy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempne him. When therfore the temptor ſhal laſche at vs w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> lyke temptacions, we maye not ſhrinke, we may not
<pb facs="tcp:23916:34"/> be afraid, we may not be diſcora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend our ſelf, wholy to CHRISTE, hange vpon him, who is wholy oures, who hath geuin him ſelf wholy to vs, ſo that ſynne, dethe, nor hel, hath no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing to do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs. CHRIST with a ineſtimable price, his owne blood hathe deliueryd vs from the tyranny of the deuil, and euer laſtinge dampnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is become our innocency, our life, and our iuſtice. Let vs take hede in any ways that we turne not our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes from CHRISTE cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed, Yf we cleue to him, we are ſet vpon a ſure and inexpugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rocke, againſte the whiche all the power of hell is able to do nothinge. So that we may boldly exclame, and euery one ſay with
<pb facs="tcp:23916:34"/> CHRISTE I prouided the Lorde afore my eys all way,<note place="margin">Pſal. xvi</note> for he is at my righte elbowe, that I ſhulde not be mouyd, therefore my harte hathe be gladde and my tonge hath reioyſed, moreouer my felſſhe ſhall reſte in hope. By faithe in CHRISTE we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſonnes of GOD, the bretherne and coheires of Chriſt, and partakers of euerlaſtinge life, by this faith departing hence, we ſhall go to the kingdome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paryd for the electe, afore the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnynge of the world. And if in the feruentnes of theſe temptacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s our faithe begin to wauer, yf we do not bere pacientlye the will of oure heuinlye Father, if oure loue towarde god waxe faint and cold, yf oure hope beginne to be feble &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:23916:35"/> weake: and therfore we begin to feare, leſt god and we be not all at a full point, but that he is yet diſpleaſyd with vs: which ten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion (ſurely) is very greuous, painful, daungerous, and hard to ouercome: we muſt call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance Chriſt to haue ſufferyd for vs ſo intollerable and inuincible tentacions: that there apperyd no help, no comfort, no refuge, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in GOD and the whole world: ſemyd to haue forſaken him, and to be againſt him: In ſomouche that he exclamyd, O my god, o my GOD why haſte thou forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me. Oh here was a greuous tentacion, A ſharpe and a bitter death that CHRISTE ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferid for vs, and all to make the way of the croſſe and deathe eaſy vnto vs. Therfore ſeing that,
<pb facs="tcp:23916:35"/> CHRISTE of his owne free wyll, caſte him ſelfe into the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge of ſo intollerable paine, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, and anxiety (GOD our moſt louinge Father beinge ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with contente) vndoubtydlye he knowith and conſyderyth our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmite, vndoubtydly he will not deale with vs accordinge to the rigour of the law, but will bere muche with vs and pardon many thinges, to our infirmity. Doth not CHRIST ſpeake to al men? dothe he not call men, when he ſaith: Come vnto me all you that do labour and are laden and I ſhal refreſh you? howe can ther be any greater conſolacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? howe could CHRISTE ſpeake more mercyfully to vs. There be many thinges that pinche, vex, and trouble man greuouſly: but
<pb facs="tcp:23916:36"/> what thinge is it that can trouble the conſcience of a ſynner, more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan he doubteth of the mercy of god, then whan he fearethe leaſte GOD will caſt him of, then wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he can not perſuade him ſelf to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue any truſt of gods mercy, but Imagine that as a witheryd mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber he ſhalbe cut of and caſt away. Here we had nede of chriſtes preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t helpe, here we had nede of ſpedy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forte, leſt this violent tempeſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerwhelme and drowne vs. But let vs not feare, CHRISTE is no diſſembler, he wyll ſtande by his worde, he wyll perfourme hys promyſe, He wyll helpe and refreſſhe. Therefore when we begynne to trymble and feare in oure conſcyence, when we begin to doubte of goddes mercy, when
<pb facs="tcp:23916:36"/> we perceaue our faithe to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Lette vs forthwith call v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon GOD, and that feruently, and that indeſinantly, leuen from the bottome of oure hart, that he tourne not his face from vs.</p>
                     <p>Lette vs power before hym all that dothe trouble vs. Let vs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe, to hym oure myſerye, oure imbecillitie, oure incredulity. Let vs crye with the diſciples, lorde increaſe oure faith.<note place="margin">Luc. xvii.</note> And with the Father of the Lunaticke. Lorde we beleue, helpe our incredulity. And w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prophet.<note place="margin">Marci. ix</note> Lorde make haſt to helpe vs. For thy mercy is aboue all thy workes. O moſte louing, O moſte mercyful father, lord god of our healthe,<note place="margin">Pſ. lxix</note> our only help and refuge. Enter not into iudgemente with thy ſeruauntes.
<pb facs="tcp:23916:37"/> Chriſte is our iuſtice, our redemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy, he for vs hathe ſufferyd moſt bitter &amp; cruel death.</p>
                     <p>Let theſe thynges moue the o father of mercy. For thys thy ſon our ſauior Chriſtes ſake haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, confirme and ſtrength our harte in faith, comfort vs with the conſolacions of thy holy ſprit, that we may finally optayne Ioy euerlaſtyng, through Ieſus chriſt Amen.</p>
                     <p>After this ſort if we (laborynge, wreſting, and ſtriuinge with our imbecillity, accuſing afore god, &amp; lamentinge our puſilianimity and incredulity) do catch hold of chriſt and cleue faſt to hym, earneſtlye and feruently deſirynge hys help, that he wyl vouchſafe to take our place &amp; to ſupply that is lackinge
<pb facs="tcp:23916:37"/> in vs. Theſe thinges if we do ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly all thinges ſhalbe well, we ſhal auoyde and eſcape eaſly all daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; peryl, we ſhalbe ſafe enogh. For theſe two, to beleue in Chriſt and with hart to deſire faith, doth not much differ the one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For though we fele yet great weaknes and imperfection in our ſelf, yet this ought to comfort vs, that god wylleth &amp; commandeth that he ſhoulde be called vpon, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath promiſed to here and help theſe, that call ryghtly vpon him. Now as nothing is more iuſtly or neceſſarily deſired the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true faith, euen ſo god hearith no praier ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or more gladly then whan ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> findyng no goodnes in hym ſelfe, doth acknowlege his owne infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, his owne myſery, his owne beggerlines, dothe accuſe and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:23916:38"/> his owne incredulity, &amp; with depe ſighes, &amp; harty deſires calleth for faith. Theſe ſighes, theſe deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, theſe prayers, this litle ſparke of faithe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſede of GOD, wrought in vs by him, which ſaith of Chriſte by the Prophet Eſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhall not quenche the ſmokinge flaxe, nor breake the bruſyd rede. Therfore let vs ſtedfaſtly beleue, or at the leaſte earneſtelye and hartely pray that we may beleue, bewaylyng afore god our lacke of faithe, whiche thinges if we do, we nede not doubt but we be acceptid of god, we be taken for his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For it is not for noughte, nor in vaine that he hathe layde our imbecillitie and ſynnes vpon his only begoten ſonnes backe.</p>
                     <p>In Mathew<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> it is ſaid bleſſed be thoſe that mourne, for thei ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:23916:38"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted, bleſſyd be thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger after righteouſnes, for they ſhalbe ſatiſfied. Theſe words are ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al ſo to vs, they may iuſtly be apply<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to vs, we mourne &amp; are ſory in our hartes that we haue miſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyd our life paſte. We wiſhe and deſyre, yea we eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honger &amp; thriſte after righteouſnes. Lette vs be of good chere, we ſhall optayne oure deſire, we ſhalbe comfortyd, we ſhall be counted iuſte a fore GOD, for CHRISTE oure ſauior his ſake. Fynally let vs after the example of Chriſt and ſainte Steuin commend our ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les into the handes of GOD our heuenly father, ſainge euery one after this maner.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O</hi> Moſt mercyfull father I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d into thy holly ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des my
<pb facs="tcp:23916:39"/> ſpirit, yea thy ſpirite, for thou haſt create it, thou haſte commytted it for a tyme to the body, thou haſte geuen it thy owne Image and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude. Thou haſte ſent for the rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption of it, thi owne moſt dere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly belouyd ſonne to ſhed his blood. This the ſpirite, I reſigne into thi han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, O GOD of all mercy, I am thyne all that I am, I be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeche the refuſe not thy owne but receaue, kepe and place me in euerlaſting glory for the ſake of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, thy only begoten ſonne Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:39"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:40"/>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Iames Burrel, dwellyng without the Northe gate of Paules in the cornor houſe of Pater noſter rowe ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge in to chepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23916:40"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
